so following on from a previous session
when we were talking about arising
passing away this will change yeah but
more interesting more more about the
arising in the passing history and we
were talking about the so the experience
as a whole imagining might say the
feeling as presently in jewelry whether
that's whether you recognize it as
arising as becoming more intense bigger
or whether it's decreasing its passing
away and and that seems like something
that everyone can just say but the but
it talks about people contemplating
arising and passing for all five
aggregates hmm so that kind of makes you
and makes you sort of okay so you know
you can recognize the arising of a mood
or you can recognize that a mood is
arising but maybe it's not quite so
straightforward to recognize what's
meant by the arising of matter or
another way of approaching it would be
the senses the body rising so like what
is the most what is the closest matter
to you
the body what is the what is the closest
sense perception to the eye but okay so
what is the eye on the level of what is
the I can you decide the odds before the
that so the body again on the basis of
your body
yeah can you have a presently duty move
whatever the mood is pleasant unpleasant
neutral without your body being there
alive that's so exactly hence you want
to contemplate the rising and ceasing
with the five aggregates you want to
quantify the rising and ceasing with the
five aggregates you need to
computerizing and the six and the body
yeah that's it it's not like for people
think for what is the arising of the
matter yeah means you you are not contemplating
yeah means you you are not contemplating
it you are obstructing it yeah to first
set to December the matter is that's
closest to you as in the only matter you
can really even indirectly experience
which is this body side and it matters
to be understood is to be understood in
the level of the body and everything
else is descending through them because
I can only exactly I can only recognize
you know talk about some external things
if dog over there but that's always you
see me sitting here my eyes yes that's
all really on the basis of your body
exactly so you try to understand
something without having understood the
base of your body means that won't be
applying to the right thing he won't be
understood yeah so you mentioned get
back get back
you mentioned the the the senses
we mentioned earlier that even this
suitors say how do you regard the I
chuckle how do you got it so I'm asking
you okay describe it describe a cone I
might ask what is what he died okay
what is the offset when you say that
first thing first thing you sort of
consider is what I'm seeing so like you
know see you which kind of right look
what if I ask you what is the eye
what are you designate buy it for
yourself when you say my eyes like this
from this eye of that eye what do you
think that - that's what I'm saying so
okay so it's only in relation to bomb
scene so yeah we've not seen that's like
when you infer a fter words how do you
get to know it yeah well I can't like
that's the thing I can't I can't
you can talk about it so what are you
talking about what is that thing because
that thing it's not like oh I am when I
see the eye I refer to the negative
aspect of the positive seeing did it
there no no that's all your
rationalization afterwards when you say
oh can you give me this I need to cover
my eyes
what are those eyes that you talk about
how do you regard that thing what is it
for you what is the significance of it
for you you're right accomplices to
lumps of flesh in the front of your face
same basic what are the theories
describe it talk about the two lumps of
fly face what else is there reveal
through the two lumps of flesh whatever
it's not like looking for but together I
so just want you to describe that
nothing else the particular bit of the
body which gets called the eye which had
to calm the eye which seems to be kind
of which I can close and then I don't
see anything
which I can stay don't really close it
but he just covered it yeah yeah yeah
yeah so there's still sort of a fakes
see yeah yeah you still see kind of hey
so so there's that mean can you
[Music] interfere or can you prevent the AI from
interfere or can you prevent the AI from
seeing no not so just by closing my eyes
I can't stop myself from seeing because
I can't stay see pink I can see sure
lines I could zoom like a chance of
light all those things I've seen yeah so
the two lumps of flesh in your face
there are your eyes yeah the organs or
the eyes you can't actually command them
so to speak you can't decide when to see
when not to see that home kind of domain
that they seem to be sure the center of
all the the the root um that whole
domain within which things appear in
that kind of way a very different way
from the light so d40 of the hearing
domain but that whole domain is just I
can't I didn't choose it for it to be
there and I can't stop it from being
there yeah so then the choice that you
can exercise over the organs lumps of
flesh of your eyes is the choice within
their domain yeah that's always a
colossal task that look at that over
that nobody have no choice about looking
down I see this place yeah the men have
seen you are subjected to yeah so what
will then be the characteristics of
something that you are subjected to and
M now say about how would you describe
that experience
well fundamental control here and that's
the thing though so recognizing than any
level of control is to it like choosing
to look at
over looking at that is undermined by
just this whole is more fundamental lack
of control over the fact that that no
choice but I'm asking you now is what
are the characteristics of being
subjected to something or anything
how does it feel so yeah okay so I guess
it's these two separate two things it's
suffering being subjected to it in
itself even if yeah even if things are
not necessarily unpleasant the failure
you know say yeah in that fundamental
level exactly being being hit by things
yeah it might be being hit by something
that's Pleasant being oppressive all
your burdens be subjected and we go
around with and that's the thing even if
everything is Pleasant in your eyes in
just in the sound in in all the senses
the fact is that like I was helping it
well exactly the fact is that because
it's Pleasant there is always the
implicit possibility of it ceasing to be
pleasant or becoming otherwise and all
that stems from that very fundamental
relationship with those things which is
a you are subjective does them not that
they are subjected to your will and even
if it's Pleasant
the fact that I was subjected to it
means I didn't choose for that budget
which means it could no and that's in
more than enough for the basis of
suffering to manifest morally not for to
cut to show itself so then you realize
that the real pleasure then it's not an
experience in pleasure and not
experiencing pain the truth pleasure as
in the the agree ability of experience
is when you when you are in control if
you were in control yeah if you are the
one who is who is sort of subjecting
things not subjected to them yeah and
the good news is that's possible as what
it said like in case of another hunt
he said his mind doesn't know about him
he overwhelms his mind but now you need
to understand how that's done in other
words he doesn't overwhelm his mind
through the power of will cause power of
will is secondary already within the domain
is secondary already within the domain
of the census including the domain of
the mind as we described it says so the
only way to then you not be overwhelmed
by the mind over wonder mind is to fully
relinquish the ownership of the mind
fully relinquish the ownership of that
which is necessarily has to be subjected
to whatever five aggregates of senses
which are approach you take that's the
only way out there is no wiggling way
out there's no like in hindsight you can
figure it out and then reapply the only
way to get out is to abandon that which
is liable to these things that are not
in your control so what is that thing
that needs to be abandoned that is
liable to things that are not in your
control that sense of self sense of self
what are the characteristics of the
sense of self described it as a field
yeah so basically in terms of feeling
it's like it's like it's like that
second arrow it's like the kind of visit
it's like a response to so there's a
feeling already there mm-hmm
but then there's also there's also other
feelings on top of that that are kind of
a response to the original feeling like
not wanting it to be there or you know
like wanting pleasure not wanting pain
and so like yeah this sort of sorts this
sort of domain of feelings that are
involved in trying to manage your
feelings but this is how the sense of
self then that seems to be that that
seems that's like when you say when you
say I am yeah look I am so-and-so what
is that I am bit of your designation of
the name of the Nama what does that
refer to
what do you say my point of view and say
but is that explicitly present when you
talk about I am that point of view is
right there yeah actually nobody's right
there yeah not like what you think
should be there or what you find when
you start looking closer when you just
casually carelessly say I am this around
that what are you referring to with that
I am because if there is truly nothing
he would be like that would be you and
so it's a whole set of so it's a whole
kind of various assumptions you know
again there's some very nice variety
it can only be secondary so what is the
thing you refer to market when you say I
am that way so the reason why we make
sure you heard of that which stuff there
isn't dirt which is there okay yeah
let's better start exactly
so what else I mean as in what are the
categories you of that which is there
that you referred to as I am that which
is dear there which is there exactly
what are the characteristic of having
things dear to you what are the
characteristics and something being
about something we think of something
that's the other thing that something
that you find pleasurable and you care
about shouldn't you that you sort of
have you you keep having this sense of
like wanting to control it somehow
because you don't want bats to come to
is it yeah there is the implication of
that in everything that you find dear
yeah and then you realize it can could
you have such an implication of control
without assuming at least a possibility
of ownership that all right so like I
say we said like somebody someone your
loved ones mmm
you.your yeah exactly loved ones you
basically I wanna say that you found
them do you think well I don't want
anything about to come with them as if I
can somehow have some say in whether
something battle comes to them so then
you could see the thread they were just
kind of revealed when you say I am
so-and-so you refer to certain general a
generality or your experience because
you can say I am is this and that's you
rationalizing afterwards in the moment
of designation when you're speaking what
you refer to is that kind of a generally
present experience as a whole
that's enduring there but yes there are
certain characteristics that implied in
you designating it with I am unless your
mind is enlightened in which say that
the Buddha said if at the target that
uses words like I am this and this is
mine without those things really meaning
that implying the ownership but if
you're not that the target that means
there is a degree of ownership implied
in those things so the first thing
people do is there is no I am then there
is no I deny it deny everything thus you
deny the problem does there is no
problem yeah the feather you can still
speak in terms of I am this or I know
this means there is still the
implication of that generality didn't
use for you that you're designating as
yours and that's exactly the point you
can't have the sense of I am without
sense of mine you can't have the sense
of I am however vague however careless
without the sense of ownership of that
general experience that in dues there
for you that you are subjected to not
subjected to you so then when you are
referring to I am you imply the
ownership of your experience as a whole
now if you say okay police the language
stop saying I am because the Buddha said
an otter he was to the garden you can
you can now something else a different
designation will take its place why
because it's the underlying view that
makes you assume the ownership thus your
language sort of replicates it so if you
are saying I am you look at it as a
symptom of is there the underlying
ownership of my attitude not in terms of
oh I must stop saying that because
that's not foolish those
that so there is no sense of I am
without the sense of ownership so then
if you want to really develop the
experience of an otter it's not about
saying there is no self it's basically
about abandoning the ownership of that
which you're designating as your sense
of self so what would be then both of
the characteristics of the ownership be
characteristic in general just a mission
of mine belongs to me
belonging to me could belong to me
Pleasant having this thing yeah that's
another thing isn't it you you you you
can't have you would not entertain the
sense of having somepony something
there's no implicit pleasure non-threat
familiarity all those things are rooted
in it's like you don't think all that's
mine yeah okay I can see that's that
which is yours body but that's not yours
cause it's given you same I can't say
you really deep down you wanna get rid
of the minus of the cancer and that's
the that's the that's the key yourself
can you then take this reflection
further sense of ownership sense of mine
is a necessary basis for me entertaining
the sense of I am as my own belong to me
so if you were to then fully understand
the sense of ownership there is a good
chance you'll be able to then not
entertain the sense of I am on the basis
of that so what are the characteristics
and further characteristics of the sense
of ownership because as the Buddha said
regarding things as mine is a mistake
beginningless mistake but it's
nevertheless the mistake so how do you
rectify the mistake
what is it that you regard as yours or
[Music]
when you regard something is mine what
are the characteristics of that thing
I mean yeah I mean asking the same
question well can you say this is mine without
well can you say this is mine without
this can you see my head okay okay so
it's always in relation to a thing
that's already given it has to be
something that's yours so which is first
and the thing that's good is if your
sense of mine comes first and then finds
things for its ownership though so that
sense of ownership is secondary to who's
completely dependent upon a thing which
happens to be given in the first place
yeah which is on the level of how we
started this the domain of vision yeah
now the particular sites sound smell
taste touches but the domain of those
senses it's pretty much already
inaccessible to you it's given you're
subjected to it and then yourself your
sense of ownership then cannot possibly
step outside of their domain or any of
those disposing fully that's fully
within yeah so is then they truly can be
called fully understanding man you say
that any sense of ownership I can
possibly have towards any of them is
really always gonna be dependent it's
only a relative ownership on account of
things they were given that you don't
own and relative ownership is more than
enough to understand correctly to
approve the ownership of what agenda
that maintains in like in theory state
of art Avada because relative ownership
it's not ownership it's not your
ownership it's like recognizing a
relative degree of control you have
within the domain and you have no
control over
I guess just saying that much they just
how well they repetitively seeing which
we just done and that's why the suitors
would go into these repetitions not like
because they were repetitive for the
sake of repetition itself but because
each repetition
it's a phenomenological description of
how should your understanding unraveling
because it's not about figuring it out
like oh yeah I got it it's about
constantly reapplying the same figuring
out on every possible for every relevant
level in case of the senses it's the
sick relevant levels so you have to keep
relevant levels so you have to keep
doing it why because if you don't do it
it's enough to just ignore certain level
and assume that you know what you
already know and to that extent you are
not free of that assumption
yeah sure you need to understand the
principle to begin with in order to know
what to apply as in as we just described
the principle of non ownership is more
fundamental than principle of ownership
ownership is secondary to it the right
order of things but then he needs to be
done repetitively in regards to the body
in regard to senses in video to be
travel way look at the mind let's do the
mind now up in terms of your point of
view isn't it we adjusting your point of
view so seeing where that point of view
actually is you regard to things rather
than because self assumes a point of
view which is beyond things that are
happening in this direction right right
I see that's what we read so how would
you do it and how would you describe
them but by seeing that there's that
point of view is surrounded by things
happening to it yeah sure
but let's let's do it let's do how we do
this your point of view
just I stopped the sentence their point
of view point of view what is the point
of view that's what suitors do by the
way when the monks is claimed things
twice first jhana 1st jhana what is 1st
jhana as in I stop I won't think about
things that are related to first jhana
until I understand the first jhana so
whatever you won't understand that's
hard to start I'm designating something
I'm throwing this thing in this
direction without being concerned in any
other direction what is it what it is
that I'm aiming it at least that so when
you say point of view describe that that
phenomena designating by calling it a point of
designating by calling it a point of
view what are the characteristics of
that phone to view your the sensor
experience the center of experience okay
that's that's that's a quite a accurate
description in a way but what are the
characteristics of that center of that
experience further have you created it
or have you just found it there yes it
is it is part of the structure very
dense there so can you look for example
if a doubt or have I created it can you
remove it can you access as you will to
say no more of this Center it's
inconceivable so then even the point of
view shares the same characteristics as
this eye domain air domain and domain of
them domain of their recent phenomena
and that's how you stop assuming the
outside point of view by seeing that
point of view point of view oh I have no
control over this so when you think
outside of the point of view that's
already within the reason structure as
you called it the external point of view
yes like the external point of view of
our Towada it's not actually external in
its content that's impossible it's only
external to the extent you ignore that
it cannot be external so take out the
vada tomate what is automatic self view
translator whichever you want or don't
restrain use the poly but then think
about it what is it referred or refers
to the self that's independent of the
final date again you're describing and
there is a phenomena they're enduring
for you and apply the same principle for
it the external point of view they still
open to be external to what then you
realize the external external aspect of
it
external Ness it's only relatively
external to the content of something
else and depend on it
exactly yes so then you realize it's not
truly external and not thinking that
clearly not clarifying that for
you maintain the notion that is true
external that I am truly independent
there is no that things are happening to
me within me you know things are
happening within my point of view well
that's that's secondary now yeah yeah so
that's the truth
there I mean that's the truth oh sure
sure sure but I'm saying that even in
that case in order to address that you
need to see that point of view first
correctly then there will be no division
in a sense of in me outside of me in
that fundamental sense of foreigner is
when there is your starting point is
then things are happening to me - what -
this Center of experience what are the
characteristics of the center experience
prevent our that's going into actually
I'm just trying to understand it yeah
someone who doesn't understand it that's
what it's like yeah okay yes sir but
what about that how's that relevant what
do those words like well if you know
trying to understand it yeah they're
yeah busy you understand it you have to
know what it's not yeah yeah yeah well
that's still the point like if you were
trying to understand it or if you want
to understand it any of those division
in me outside of me happening to me
that's all fine but if you want to
understand it you have to go beyond it
because all of those divisions that you
talk about aren't the result of you
already appropriate in the point of view
because which you can't if you look at
it closely it becomes impossible to
appropriate because it has arisen on its
own so you're saying that anyone she
understood it can you understand what
you mean this was exactly yeah in
hindsight you can't understand what
ignorance is what is still ignorant of
that ignorance yeah it's exactly the
point I was making
so trying to understand it start
revealing what's going on which happens
to be an enjoyment yeah however it's
important as we done there before as
well to clarify that revealing what's
going on can often become psychologizing
for people not in this particular cases
you've done but in general people think
that if I don't start talking about this
I'm revealing it no you must stay with
the first phenomena you started to
designate and understand that then when
you take that further understand the
next one that's why I said of the point
of view is the center of my tears wet
point of view point what is the point of
view describe the characteristics you've
done so put it aside center of
experience what are the characteristics
of that so that's how you get to undo
your ignorance now we're figuring out on
account of ignorant premises but by
questioning every single premise that
you started with and then yeah yeah you
wouldn't understand how you were
ignorant before tell us it feels like
things are happening within me you
shouldn't say that that's actually right
exactly thinks it's far a good
experience always feels like there
things are happening in me okay
in me in me what are the characteristics
of that how does that feel things
happening in you yeah this is kind of
imagine it say sometimes I mean you how
would you well let you you you surround
the things okay in in me means that
things are happening in me that I I am
surrounded I surround those things like what like what
[Music]
I'm going to think of example yeah yeah
well just not everything is happening I
think the most obvious example would for
people would be thoughts thoughts are in
my hair for telling me yeah I'm thinking
more even with what I'm seeing
okay but they can ease up a little on my
experience so whatever is that what
you're saying inside inside inside my
experience so that explain that that
entails that implies then the opposite
yet so how can you experience an
opposite if everything you can
experience inside or outside of it yeah
so can then the opposite can then the
outside of you be experienced if your
own experience is always inside of you
how can you then know what's outside
unless you experience it inside in which
case it's not outside at moment so then
when you think inside you implicitly
determine the outside that's not this
inside which you can experience which
you can then experience but then can
there be inside without any outside
that's in experienceable then you really
can't then you realize also that this
inside is all you have so then any
division between inside and outside are
on the inside so that's that's going
back to the basic experience is itself
then is is a thing which if you don't
look at first of all because it's the
fall apart
it is not seen selfies basically not
under for there to be any self it needs
to be not understood sure of nature it's
in ignorance I'm seeing things yeah
which ones it seems to be there because
as soon as you start looking in that
direction yeah but I'm still I'm still
basically on the inside outside how's
that connect to that damage
percent yourself in a sense of insider
well cuz it implies that you are outside
the other side implies the you're
outside origin to self it that's I am
beyond vet which is in its night yeah
okay here you can start with that so
let's use that as a basis and that is
the characteristic pretty much of
everything is happening to me thus I am
basically the outsides of this yes well
that's exactly the kind of the car
itself yeah industry and eternal lasting
yeah industry and eternal lasting
forever area non-dependent of these
things well that's the whole point you
you don't negate that but you need to
understand it and you won't understand
it but kind of not
you won't understand it by thinking on
the basis of it you will understand it
by undoing the basis of it as in they
are doing the lack of understanding of
the basis of it
so the experience of things are
happening to me it's fine that's the
starting point so what is that as we
said sense of me that we described oh
there's a sense of ownership there's a
sense of things are liable to these
things happening so like things are
happening to this body things are
happening to the senses and you get
involved by assuming the ownership of it
because if you start looking closely you
realize you have no control over the
domain of eyes no control over the
domain of ears and so on so then if you
were to remove them the ownership you
would then remove that equal
self-centered sense of I am and this
happening to me but if you try to sort
of figure out internally and externally
and then how you relate to it it won't
be on the same fundamental level of
undoing the premise of self that you
took for granted so it's not me like
when you describe this kinda sense of
self as we just done but if you already
thinking of sense of self needs to be
figured out show and it's happening to
me doing all these divisions all of
these ways of thinking are already
secondary to you have taken the
ownership of it and the sense of self
hence every individual thing basically
can then serve as a base for
understanding the principle they would
apply to whole but if you're not looking
to understand the principle then no
matter we need we of individual things
can bring their kind of the whole
picture because it's already secondary
to that so things are happening to me
it's not necessarily the best basis to
start because things are happening to me
or not doesn't really matter it's it's a
bit abstract things are happening to me
and I'm the sense of self in regards to
K but then I would ask you why is that a
problem presumably whoever wants to
understand this wants to freed himself
from the sense of self why that's what I
mean like you you do need to know like
what to ask for and then he needs to be
asked to the right level so yeah that's
why the instruction of another and
confidence of another is necessary
because people asking what is self
something but they don't necessarily so
and so by going my direction which I've
said is you always the self is this
amazing eternal I am thing that's just
indescribable and everything like this
like in the suit is often people will
come to myself and it is a great it is a
bit larger phenomenal sure sure but as
if you do not you want the highest sense
yeah the mystical experience is real it
is higher in a sense then
and anything else they could never
possibly imagine everything but if you
want to be honest intellectually honest
yourself can you know a higher self
unless you're experiencing it right here
right now unless he has a reason has
manifested porous enduring as a
phenomenon no mystical exactly she's
just higher in its content as in he has
a less defined content less mundane
content but in its nature it's still
there is a thing that restored upon us
understanding is whatever has a nature
of manifesting that's why it's
impairment not or not that he denies
that something's manifest at the higher
level something's in the lower doesn't
matter and that's what I say whatever
they angry is it like whatever's matter
form metal feeling perception so
whatever aggregate is far or near low or
high personal impersonal present past
few whichever he understands aggregate
or matter is there he understands
aggregate as in he understand the nature
of phenomenon is present doesn't matter
what or on what level so even if
somebody cherishes the sense of I am
unless they forsake the criteria of
intellectual honesty they still not
beyond hope in terms of if they want to
understand they still have a basis for
that understanding so you can be as
mystical as you want and proliferate
your sense of self as far as you wish
and that's not really the problem
depends where you come in from what you
watch you modulate exactly that's the
problem if you sort of never ever and
you choose that never ever go in the
direction of questioning it or in
questioning yourself in regard to it
that's the worst thing you can do like
you can be ignorant and everything else
you still have a thread of possibility
to pull yourself out of it but if you
are fully willingly cemented yourself in
your own product of your own wrong view
that's the worst thing you can do as in
by that I mean no no I will not think
about that
why would I question the sense herself
because sense itself is the greatest
that's why you question it you don't
need the reason to question things and
that's why the Buddha did say that the
most blameworthy things
in the entire basically samsara is the
wrong view nothing else can can come on
the same level as bad as a wrong view
because it's a direct reason why people
do everything else that's unwholesome
and the kids didn't bind to their to the
wanderings and so on so even if
somebody's mystical I am this I am this
Graham this lofty I have this mystical
experience okay fine
describe the characteristics of that you
had a mystical experience of this higher
self did you have a say in a
manifestation will you clean how can you
even create something actually when you
think about it from that from
nothingness how can you create something
it for which that thing wasn't and you
haven't thought about it because they
will order to be then thing so you are
unaware I'm knowing I'm conscious of
this thing and suddenly you created how
can that possibly happen in
inconceivable so then the experience of
the higher self that a person might have
had oh I was subjected to it in the same
sense up subjected to sight sound smell
taste are just thoughts ideas
experiences what are the characteristics
of being subjected to these things oh I
can't on them even if I want so then my
lofty mystical experience of higher self
was just another reason think because of
that it's impermanent because of that it
cannot beyond unburnable Lomita so this
great high sense of self that i had is
this lofty to me lasted for weeks I was
in this bliss cannot beyond devalues
everything that's based on passion
that's basis the wrong field but that's
anyway it's in its that mystic limb yes
in a good position in a way he's very
close sure yeah that's the thing
close oh really really far depending on
the motivation behind his mystical view
mystical view in itself
yeah it's a wrong view but it doesn't
necessarily mean the person who holds it
is like as I said beyond repair he might
be quite close
if he's not forsaking that
self-questioning even in regard to his
greatest pleasure of his enlightens and
so fire self because if he's abandoning
all things sure he's abandoning all
things all things will end there just by
keeping hold of that
yes myself yeah that's the last thing
you know and that's how you can see if
somebody who is refusing to abandon that
- he's actually worse off there's
somebody who didn't abandon all these
things but hasn't developed that
deeply-rooted wrong view either so
that's what we need it's rooted in
motivation on the self in the content of
you if you abandon man-thing you've
abandoned yeah yeah if you abandon that
kind of someone to a person abandons but
the thing that he's supposed to abandon
and another person abandons everything
else exactly
and what's that one person abandons one
thing and the other person don't that's
exactly the difference between sotapanna
in the suitors who Kenan who abandons
the rock theatre bada he bends us that
self of you but doesn't abandon
sensuality yet doesn't abandon conceit
yet and all these other things yet you
have people who dizziness who can
abandon sensuality can abandon the
Virgin Duty can abandon all the other
but not the death of that one and that's
I mean if somebody has arrived at
abandoning all these other things
without abandoning the right diet Avada
practically speaking to be more unlikely
they will abandon it because they've
invested but if man abandons the right
thing to begin with that's actually been
caused in a long run you will then
arrive in a complete liberation in the
long run this person what if religion
abandoned sensuality in this life that's
great but if he abandon sensuality on account
but if he abandon sensuality on account
of deeply rooting the wrong view of a
mystical experience that's not great in
other words his non-central behavior in
this life can probably result in you
know better rebirth next time coming
around he's going to be in a better
position but fundamentally the wrong
view will be more and more
so sooner or later when that runs out
he's back where he started but somebody
who is understood the Buddhist teaching
who has an abandoned sensuality who has
an abandoned sensuality yet but has
abandoned the wrong view means he will
have to abandon sensuality sexuality and
everything else as a result of that
because it's the most deeply rooted
wrong view that kind of implies all the
other wrong views but yeah you know
where he has abandonment exactly for we
know yes he is uprooted it yeah but the
roots they were uprooted still have some
life in them but they cannot remain
alive forever because they're not being
fed anymore and that's why it's
important to recognize that when you
read the sutras as well often people get
kind of caught up and bogged into
content and all this and decides that it
needs to be understood on the level of
the domains on the level of the nature
of things so I had a mystical experience
of a lofty self like you couldn't put it
in the words okay
that's your experience what are the
characteristics of that so looking the
content that you could have put in the
words describe the nature it for
yourself because there must be something
there otherwise as I said speech would
not be possible we wouldn't be able to
designate it so originally we talked
about the eye the arising of the eye we
talked about the characteristics of the
eye
so how would you describe someone
contemplating arising of the eye passing
away at the eye
I mean mommy thought I'd be right or
sorry I'm trying to fit on a plane
because like we said say you know it's
quite easy to recognize the arising of a
feeling there's a disability that are
feeling well that are feeling so me you
so it is again present we Charles
whichever way you were to go continent
well whatever thing you were to
contemplate rightly as in the rising
passing away of it intensifying or
fading away needs to be done on that
right level of generality so to speak if
you're not on the right level you again
you can get to it but trying to do it
but you need to understand it you can
only contemplate theorizing of the ID
passing where you're going not by the
extra line but on the level of the
experience is about is a whole which is
it sally ayanna yeah and you pointed it
out it's it's singular yeah six sense
bases its success base exactly it's a
base made out of six yeah but on the
level of base it's a one base it's a
wonderful Amin ah yeah
within that you can contemplate the
direction of the I in the direction of
the air the direction of you but not at
the expense of it super even that
practically rectification it sets the
tension of the intensification of the
body how did you reveal that how did you
become aware of it gonna count of
something that's this present enduring
on the on the domain of the visual
something so impactful something so
significant that you just see that's it
or even just like I wasn't really like
my eyes closed and then suddenly I kind
of like not the back gets rid of the
domain oh yeah sure but you're not
really attending to what you're seeing
maybe you got your eyes closed you're
thinking about I don't know something
another you then look at so you submit
the bird appears you suddenly start
looking at the bed and you're suddenly
morning it doesn't mean the visual
domain surely wasn't there exactly so if
you want to intensified so doesn't mean
that it wasn't arising exactly we'll see
see exactly before
you saw it so you you get to discern
whether that's arising or CC if you get
to discern it peripherally without even
having to attend what you're staring at
so if there is a knowledge of the visual
domain for example persisting that's
already mindfulness of either arising or
either seasick because as we established
before now you're a rising or ceasing is
something you are responsible yeah but
you were responsible in a being of
basically we're mindful of that which
has arising or CC yeah so if the arising
and the ceasing is so peripherally not
closing the sizing for the lack of a
better word not losing the sight of the
visual domain so if anybody now is
paying attention to what you're looking
at
that's your gate keeping of the visual
domain that set and so so there's
basically all of these domains the I
thought the body which ever you can even
imagine you gets the five aggregates all
of those things endure and while they're
enduring they're either intensifying
coordinated to find it in a kind of
relative sense relative to each other
no that's again assuming your tiny
citizen relative means you agree to come
to know it's neither this already talked
about this and use how you compare this
is there know the feeling is stronger
than the perception there exactly no
it's just as long as you recognize that
those five things endure enduring they
sort of just their hmm they will be
either within themselves from the
perspective of that phenomenon this way
and then then do you realize there isn't
anything there doesn't have to be
anything I guess that try to compare things or it
I guess that try to compare things or it
assumes a sense of that you can
dependent of things yeah which is nice
happy and that's all usually people
would misunderstand the Buddha when he
would when he would list these things
and you would say yeah I did
I actually like ladle out in front of
you here that's how you and I
understand it and you're just
maintaining selfie yeah that would be
true if you could truly step outside so
which you can't which means these things
need to be understandably understood in
a different level yeah that's wait for
logician that is the suitors you would
think of this is just otology yeah cuz
it is from a logical point of it's just
minute ontology cuz it you all laid it
out there in itself everything truth I
think it is ok so what did the Buddha
say if you understand this
what's the result of that oh it's
complete freedom from suffering an
undulation of passion and anger
everything somehow will free from those
things no means I'm not understanding it
the way they would intended it to be but
if you don't think that far then you
would end up thinking you understood the
suitors while still not being free from
suffering in everything else so I have
developed an understanding of these
things but that's not what's being
spoken about is it there must be more
because I'm not getting the results did
they say the standing seems to say you
should be happy